A Finding Aid to the Anne Wilson Papers, 1977-2012, in the Archives of American Art AAA.wilsanne
Archives of American Art
Anne Wilson papers
1977-2012
AAA.wilsanne
Archives of American Art
1.4 Linear feet
The papers of the visual artist and educator Anne Wilson measure 1.4 linear feet and date from 1977-2012. The papers primarily document her career through biographical material and printed material. The bulk of this collection is made up of exhibition materials and magazines that feature Wilson but also included are examples of her work as a guest curator.
Wilson, Anne, 1949-
Biographical/Historical note
Anne Wilson (1949- ) is a visual artist who lives and works in Evanston, Illinois. She is a professor of Fiber and Material Studies at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago and continues to exhibit her own work around the country.
After graduating with a BFA from Cranbrook Academy of Art, Wilson moved to the Bay Area in California. While living there between 1972 and 1979, she completed her MFA at the California College of the Arts. During her time in California, she also served as a guest curator for two exhibits, both at the Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco’s Downtown Center.
In 1979 she started teaching at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago as a Professor of Fiber and Material Studies. Beginning in California and continuing to today, her work has been consistently exhibited all over the United States as well as in England. Wilson considers herself more of a visual artist than a fiber artist because her work often includes components of sculpture, drawings, performances and video in addition to the elements more often associated with a fiber artist. She is also known for using human hair in her pieces.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2013 by Anne Wilson.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 2 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1977-2012 (7 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Printed Material, 1978-2012 (1.2 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of the visual artist and educator Anne Wilson measure 1.4 linear feet and date from 1977-2012. The papers primarily document her career through biographical material and printed material. The bulk of this collection is made up of exhibition materials and magazines that feature Wilson but also included are examples of her work as a guest curator.
Related Archival Materials note
Also in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview of Anne Wilson conducted July 6 and 7, 2012, by Mija Riedel.
Curators--Illinois; Fiber artists--Illinois; Women artists--Illinois
- Biographical Material, 1977-2012; Series 1; 7 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are a curriculum vitae, an artist’s statement, a published interview (including a PDF on a CD), and installation photos, exhibition flyers, and booklets, regarding two exhibitions in which the artist acted as a guest curator.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artist Statement, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Published Interview with Victor Cassidy, 2011; Includes 1 CD-R. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Files, "The Cover Story", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Exhibition Files, "A Weaver's Art", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Printed Material, 1978-2012; Series 2; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Printed material consists of exhibition flyers and catalogs for shows in which the artist participated, photo copies of articles and books, magazines in which the artist and her works are featured, award programs that the artist received, and reviews and essays regarding the artist (some included on a CD).
  - Exhibtion Flyers, 1978-2012 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1978-2011 (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Magazines, 1984-2008 (Box 1, Folder 14-18)
  - Magazines, 2008-2012 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Award Programs, 1989-2012 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Anne Wilson Selected Reviews and Essays, 1993-2011; Includes 1 CD-R. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1981-2012 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Postcards, 1986-2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Books, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)